<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Clirr</title>
        <author>Lars Kühne</author>
        <meta name="keyword" content="java, api, diff, compare, jar, binary, compatibility, compatible, detect, incompatibility, incompatible"/>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="What is it?">
            <p>
Clirr is a tool that checks Java libraries for binary and source compatibility
with older releases. Basically you give it two
sets of jar files and Clirr dumps out a list of changes in the public api.
The Clirr Ant task can be configured to break the build if it detects
incompatible api changes. In a continuous integration process Clirr can
automatically prevent accidental introduction of binary or source compatibility
problems.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Background">
            <p>
To learn more about binary compatibility of Java APIs the follwing articles
provide some detailed background material:
                <ul>
                    <li>
the article
                        <a href="http://eclipse.org/eclipse/development/java-api-evolution.html">Evolving
Java-based APIs</a> on the Eclipse web site.
                    </li>
                    <li>
the
                        <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jls/second_edition/html/binaryComp.doc.html">Binary Compatibility</a>
section in the Java Language specification.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>

        </section>

        <section name="Features">
            <ul>
                <li>Report all API changes (currently only partially implemented)</li>
                <li>Evaluate each change wrt. binary and source compatibility</li>
                <li>support plain text and XML reports</li>
                <li>Flexible failure handling (warnings vs. errors, break the build or set error property)</li>
            </ul>

        </section>

        <section name="Name">
            <p>
        The name clirr is derived from the binary compatibility property
        that a new release of a library/component should have (cited from
        the above mentioned Eclipse article):
            </p>
            <p>
        Pre-existing
                <em>C</em>lient binaries must
                <em>li</em>nk and
                <em>r</em>un with new
                <em>r</em>eleases of the Component without recompiling.
            </p>
            <p>
        You can also use clirr as a verb, as in
                <cite>Last night the build clirred</cite>,
        meaning that binary incompatibility problems were detected and broke the build.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="License">
<p>
Clirr: compares two versions of a java library for binary compatibility
</p>
<p>
Copyright (C) 2003 - 2006 Lars Kühne
</p>
<p>
   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at
</p>
<pre>
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
</pre>
<p>
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
